如果你玩过躲猫猫，感觉宝宝好像提前知道你要出现——
这种直觉是有真实的发展心理学研究支撑的。
If you've ever played peekaboo and felt like your baby somehow
knew what was coming, that intuition is backed by real developmental psychology.
在学会说话之前，婴儿就已经在预测社交模式、
探测因果关系，并且储存对新动作的简单记忆。
Long before babies can talk, they're already predicting social patterns,
detecting cause and effect, and storing simple memories of new actions.
在这个视频中，我会带你了解四个经典的婴儿心理学实验，
以及如何做到不把趣味观察变成过度解读。
In this video, I'll walk through four classic infant experiments you can adapt at home,
and how to do them without turning a playful observation into an overblown conclusion.
首先，最重要的前提：这些不是诊断测试。
First, the big caveat: these are not diagnostic tests.
一次家庭观察无法告诉你宝宝是超前还是落后。
把它们当作精心观察的游戏就好。
A single home session cannot tell you whether your baby is advanced,
delayed, or anything in between. Think of these as carefully observed games.
四个实验遵循同样的基本规则：选择清醒安静的宝宝，
保持房间安静，宝宝烦躁就立即停止，保持时间简短。
For all four, use the same ground rules: choose a calm, alert baby,
keep the room quiet, stop if your baby fusses, and keep the session short.
实验一是躲猫猫——但作为一套真正的实验方案来做。
Experiment one is peekaboo, but done as a real protocol.
1970年代，Bruner 提出躲猫猫有严格的结构：
消失、悬念和揭晓。重复结构给了婴儿可以预测的东西。
In the 1970s, Bruner argued that peekaboo works because it has a rigid structure:
disappearance, suspense, and reveal. That gives babies something to predict.
在家里，每次做三四轮完全一致的：对视、准备提示、
遮住脸、暂停两秒、同样的表情揭开。
At home, keep the script identical for three or four trials: eye contact,
the same ready cue, cover, pause two seconds, then reveal.
基线稳定后，只改变一个变量。
延迟揭开，从另一侧出现，或者让正中短暂空着。
Once that baseline is stable, change one thing.
Delay the reveal. Reveal from the wrong side.
你要观察的是预期反应：揭开前的微笑、
暂停时的身体紧张，或目光看向预期你出现的位置。
What you're watching for is anticipation: a smile before the reveal,
body tension during the pause, or eyes going where they expected you.
关键不是宝宝"理解"了游戏，而是这个简单的社交互动
已经在给他们一个可以学习和预测的结构。
The point is not that your baby understands the game. It's that even this
simple social routine is giving them a structure they can learn and predict.
实验二是静止脸范式——可选的，因为它最敏感。
Experiment two is the still-face paradigm,
and this one is optional because it's the most sensitive.
Tronick 发现，当父母突然变得面无表情且不回应时，
婴儿会很快做出抗议。
Tronick's classic finding was that when a normally responsive parent
suddenly goes neutral and unresponsive, babies protest quickly.
家庭版很简单：一分钟正常互动，最多三十秒静止脸，
然后立即重新互动。把它当作一个严格限时的观察。
The home version is simple: one minute of normal warm play,
up to thirty seconds of still face, then immediate reunion.
如果宝宝哭了、脸红了，或者你自己不舒服，
立刻停止。重新互动不是可选项。
If your baby cries, turns red, or if you feel uncomfortable,
stop right away. The reunion is not optional.
这说明大约四到五个月时，婴儿已经期待
社交伙伴给予及时回应。当模式被打破时，他们注意到了。
It shows that by four to five months, babies already expect social partners
to respond contingently. When that pattern breaks, they notice.
实验三可能是视觉效果最明显的。
Experiment three may be the most visually rewarding.
经典研究中，婴儿学会了踢腿能让头顶的东西动起来。
在家最安全的版本使用地面健身架和全程手动监护。
In the classic studies, babies learned that kicking made something happen overhead.
At home, the safest version uses a floor play gym and full hands-on supervision.
先观察两分钟无连接的正常踢腿，
然后连上让踢腿带动玩具，最后再断开。
First, watch two minutes of normal kicking with no connection.
Then add a loose connection so kicking moves the toy. Then remove it again.
观察的核心在于阶段对比。连接后踢腿是否更有目的性？
断开后是否出现爆发性踢腿，像是在试图让效果重现？
The observation lives in the contrast between phases. Does kicking become
more deliberate when the toy responds? Do you see a burst after disconnect?
这就是因果探测：注意到"我做了这个，那个就发生了"。
这本身就很了不起，不需要过度解读。
That's contingency detection: noticing that when I do this, that happens.
It's remarkable on its own. You don't need to inflate it.
实验四是模仿——这里谨慎的版本才重要。
Experiment four is imitation, and here the careful version matters.
"新生儿会模仿表情"的说法验证得并不好。
更可靠的证据出现得稍晚，涉及对物体动作的模仿。
The flashy claim that newborns imitate faces has not held up well.
The stronger evidence comes a little later, with object actions.
从最简单的版本开始：用摇铃做一个不寻常的动作三次，
交给宝宝，安静等待。部分模仿就算成功。
Start with the easiest version: perform an unusual action with a rattle
three times, then hand it over and wait silently. A partial copy counts.
对大一点的宝宝，可以加入延迟：示范后收起来，
做别的事十分钟，再不提示地拿回来。这区分了即时模仿和记忆。
For older babies, add a short delay: demonstrate, put the object away,
do something else for ten minutes, then bring it back with no reminder.
重要的不是完美的复制，而是宝宝是否保留了
他们所看到的动作的某种表征。
What matters is not perfect copying. It's whether your baby retained
some representation of the action they saw.
家庭实验和随意玩耍的区别，在于你如何记录。
The difference between a home experiment and random play
is how you write it down.
记录你看到了什么，而不是你觉得那意味着什么。
"踢腿变多了"是观察。"理解了因果"是解读。
Record what you saw, not what you think it means.
"Baby kicked more" is an observation. "Baby understood cause and effect" is interpretation.
时机、气质和运气是巨大的干扰因素。一次试验是有趣的，
但跨越不同天数的模式才更有说服力。
Timing, temperament, and sheer luck are huge confounders.
A single trial is interesting. A pattern across different days is much more informative.
我喜欢这些实验不是因为它们证明了什么宏大的东西，
而是它们让早期认知变得可见。
What I love about these experiments is not that they prove something grand.
It's that they make early cognition visible.
躲猫猫——预测。静止脸——社会期待。
踢腿——因果探测。模仿——记忆的一瞥。
Peekaboo lets you watch prediction. Still-face reveals social expectation.
Kick-to-move shows cause and effect. Imitation gives you a glimpse of memory.